when a large language model generates
text there's a parameter that can be set
called temperature which in a manner of
speaking controls how creative it is to
understand temperature you first have to
understand that large language models
are originally trained to take in a
passage of text and predict what word or
other common character combination comes
next this prediction looks like some
kind of probability distribution when
these models generate new text like an
answer to a user question with a chatbot
what's going on is that a full context
describing the interaction is input into
the model the model predicts what word
comes next it takes a random sample from
the distribution that it generates it
appends that random choice to the full
context and then it runs it all again on
this extended text to make another
prediction and take another sample and
so on and so on over and over the
temperature is a way to modify the
probability distributions that it
generates if you set a high temperature
it gives more weight to the less likely
Words which essentially gives the model
a better chance of selecting unusual
phrases and ideas whereas a low
temperature makes it more likely to
choose the most predictable words
there's more to say but as always the
full video goes into the full details